<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="false">
  <title>Feed</title>
  <link href="/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2026-02-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>false</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Realistic - 16 to 20 February</title>
    <link href="/weeknotes/22-02-2026/"/>
    <updated>2026-02-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>/weeknotes/22-02-2026/</id><content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      <![CDATA[
<h2 id="work-week" tabindex="-1" class="govuk-heading-l">Work week</h2>
<p class="govuk-body">Bit of a reality check, after thinking about <a href="/weeknotes/14-02-2026" class="govuk-link">fun at work last week</a>.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">Over this week our small but mighty team has had blockers and unexpected events pop up, each one potentially derailing us ahead of our launch date. Cumulatively this reached a point where on Thursday morning we made a tough call on what can be realistically delivered next week.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">We’ve been offered support for the team, so there’s still a chance to meet the original scope. Even so I hope we’ve learned:</p>
<ul class="govuk-list govuk-list--bullet">
<li>everything will always take longer than expected, and things will always go wrong - so build in that expectation, avoid 100% guarantees to other stakeholders, always have an acceptable plan B agreed</li>
<li>we can be more confident in explaining right from the start how precarious technical delivery is going to be with a short timeframe and a small team</li>
</ul>
<p class="govuk-body">On the plus side it has been great to see the core team pull together, especially the newer members. We’re bringing our own strengths, supporting each other, working things through. It’s definitely been a bonding experience, which should help with future challenges.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">Myself, as we’re temporarily short of experienced management roles (who know how to navigate the organisation) I’ve been stepping in to support every other bit of delivery, and almost park my actual design role. I’ve had to reckon with how the resulting context switching and extended responsibility has affected both my mood in and out of work, and my physical ability to actually do work. There was a point on Thursday where I felt totally jammed, which hasn’t happened for a long, long time. So yes, it’s all experience for the future CV/interviews, but also something to think carefully about if this becomes a regular situation.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">Weirdly, a job ad in another department popped up this week which is almost a carbon copy of this temporary super-hybrid role I’ve ended up in the last 2 weeks (delivery management-service-designer-plus-content-and frontend-design-and-ops-thereof-oh-and-also-product management). All I can say, from my brief experience, is “errr I’m totally not sure it’s a realistic, sustainable, full time role for one person, maybe…?”.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">Amongst this have managed a couple of good chats with like-minded people in adjacent and not so adjacent parts of the organisation, helping with perspective and sparking ideas. It’s a good place because of good people, ultimately.</p>
<h2 id="other-things" tabindex="-1" class="govuk-heading-l">Other things</h2>
<p class="govuk-body">Set up the next meetup day for public sector folk in Sheffield on Tuesday 17 March, loads of interest already - if you’re round the South Yorkshire area, join us! <a href="https://forms.office.com/e/iZjT0cNisu" class="govuk-link">Find out more and sign up for X-Gov Sheffield breakfast/lunch</a>.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">Attended a helpful design community session about pitching for Service Design in Government. No excuses now.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">Played tag rugby on Tuesday evening in -2C, and really struggled physically over the next couple of days. So maybe I’m just ill 🤷.</p>
<h2 id="reading" tabindex="-1" class="govuk-heading-l">Reading</h2>
<ul class="govuk-list govuk-list--bullet">
<li><a href="https://rummanamin.co.uk/tackling-technical-debt-without-stopping-delivery/" class="govuk-link">Tackling technical debt without stopping delivery</a></li>
<li><a href="https://laurenleek.substack.com/p/britain-lost-14000-third-places-they" class="govuk-link">Britain Lost 14,000 Third Places. They Were Called Pubs. Is Your Local Next?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://tomloosemorework.wordpress.com/2026/02/19/ai-and-the-end-of-friction-as-a-policy-lever/" class="govuk-link">AI and the end of friction as a policy lever</a></li>
<li><a href="https://digitalbydefault.com/2026/02/21/a-decade-later-launching-the-ons-website-in-2016/" class="govuk-link">A decade later – launching the ONS website in 2016</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.scroll.co.uk/scroll-blog/how-to-design-a-style-guide" class="govuk-link">How to design a style guide (that people can actually use)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://contentdesign.london/blog/the-public-deserves-services-that-are-useful-usable-and-safe" class="govuk-link">The public deserves services that are useful, usable and safe</a></li>
</ul>

      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hack - 9 to 13 February</title>
    <link href="/weeknotes/14-02-2026/"/>
    <updated>2026-02-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>/weeknotes/14-02-2026/</id><content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      <![CDATA[
<h2 id="work-week" tabindex="-1" class="govuk-heading-l">Work week</h2>
<p class="govuk-body">The week started with the decision on platform choice we’ve been treading water waiting for. Happily it’s ended up nearer to the <a href="/weeknotes/07-02-2026" class="govuk-link">third way I’d advocated last week</a>: Launching a stripped down ‘beta’ site using our established tech and frontend, while setting expectations that more functionality and content will be coming through a public roadmap.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">But then of course the real work starts, and with a gnarly hard deadline coming up fast before the end of the month. So lots of getting the team together, setting clear goals each day, working out what really needs doing and where we need others onside. We’re also working radically in the open (compared to our wider team) using the justification that it will save time all round.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">It was typically hard crunchy work for first 2 days. First to define, agree and communicate our scope, then some rapid design and tech decision making, but amazingly we were already set to demo a prototype site to a group of cross-government stakeholder/users by Wednesday afternoon. I wasn’t there (still non-working/parenting day Wednesdays for me, going strong since 2022💪 ) but judging by feedback, the team, including brand new content designer, seems to have smashed the session out of the park.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">Building and maintaining trust with users in departments is maybe the most important part of our work. Our approach has been to carefully explain not just what we’re confident in, but also where we’re less certain, especially about future plans. We’re also constantly asking for input and feedback to learn about the realities of departments we’re looking to support. It’s really heartening to see this honest approach get buy in from our leaders and those outside the organisation.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">The end of my week did get consumed by too much domain wrangling and testing set up, and not enough design, but I’m still confident that <em>something</em> useful will be in place by deadline.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">On a less positive note, our preferred candidate for the user researcher role to support all this work long term has dropped out. Not quite unexpected, but we may need to get creative to fill this position sooner than the 5 months it took to not get someone in at all.</p>
<h2 id="hack-a-thon" tabindex="-1" class="govuk-heading-l">Hack-a-thon</h2>
<p class="govuk-body">Amongst the above, I was somehow able to keep a 2.5 hour block in my calendar free to take part in the latest <a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/connecting-design-systems-hack-2-tickets-1981741887332" class="govuk-link">Design System Hackathon</a> run by GDS, and the Ministry of Justice team running the new <a href="https://dev.reuselibrary.service.justice.gov.uk/" class="govuk-link">GOV Reuse Library</a>.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">I’m very glad I blocked out the time. The facilitators did a great job setting a playful tone and leading a group of 100+ through a fully online ‘hack’ session.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">Our goal was to ‘inspire’ a team starting to look at improving how designers and devs building services can discover and use components and patterns in the ecosystem of public sector design systems that now exist. For example:</p>
<ul class="govuk-list govuk-list--bullet">
<li><a href="https://design-system.service.gov.uk/" class="govuk-link">GOV.UK Design System</a></li>
<li><a href="https://design-patterns.service.justice.gov.uk/" class="govuk-link">Ministry of Justice Design System</a></li>
<li><a href="https://designsystem.gov.scot/" class="govuk-link">Scottish Government Design System</a></li>
<li><a href="https://service-manual.nhs.uk/design-system" class="govuk-link">NHS Design System</a></li>
<li><a href="https://service-manual.ons.gov.uk/design-system" class="govuk-link">Office for National Statistics Design System</a></li>
<li><a href="https://design-system.dwp.gov.uk/components" class="govuk-link">Department for Work and Pensions Design System</a></li>
</ul>
<p class="govuk-body">My lovely group had a lot of fun fleshing out our idea: ‘The Great Design System Bakeoff’, a 3 day challenge where teams of cross gov digital people compete to build the most chimeric public sector service possible, with the winners voted for by the wider community. Our proposition was this would:</p>
<ul class="govuk-list govuk-list--bullet">
<li>take advantage of the current situation where learning about design systems is often reliant on relationships and connections</li>
<li>build relationships and community across organisations (and therefore shared understanding of different systems)</li>
<li>leverage the power of “razzmatazz” to highlight the various systems and the valuable work of UCD teams</li>
</ul>
<figure><img src="/assets/images/blog/designsystembakeoff.jpg" alt="A mockup of a poster for our proposed competition. The 4 hosts and judges of the original 'bakeoff' TV show are behind a table covered in a blue and white checked table cloth. On the tables are various incredible cakes and fancy looking buns. The faces of the hosts have been covered by the logos for GOV.UK, DWP, Scottish Government, Home Office and Ministry of Justice. We've clumsily edited the original bakeoff logo to read 'Great Design System Bakeoff' by pasting over the word 'British'."><figcaption>Mockup of a poster for our proposed competition</figcaption></figure>
<p class="govuk-body">No idea if this will prove useful to the facilitators (most ideas were a little more grounded and had less photoshopping of Noel and Prue). But since the GDS Design community session last week I’ve been thinking a lot about ‘having fun’ at work, and the serious benefits that can result. This felt a perfect opportunity to give that a go, so am excited to see what happens next.</p>
<h2 id="to-do" tabindex="-1" class="govuk-heading-l">To do</h2>
<ul class="govuk-list govuk-list--bullet">
<li>Set up the next ‘X-Gov Sheffield meetup’ for Tuesday 3 March</li>
<li>Enjoy the Winter Olympics while we have it. It’s ridiculous and great, isn’t it.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="reading" tabindex="-1" class="govuk-heading-l">Reading</h2>
<ul class="govuk-list govuk-list--bullet">
<li><a href="https://www.thecontentwrangler.com/p/shifting-roles-from-content-professionals" class="govuk-link">Shifting Roles - From Content Professionals to Ontologists</a></li>
<li><a href="https://visitmy.website/2026/02/11/leadership-health-metrics/" class="govuk-link">Leadership health metrics</a></li>
<li><a href="https://futureobservatory.org/news/sheffield-design-lab-uk2040" class="govuk-link">Sheffield Design Lab</a></li>
<li><a href="https://cutlefish.substack.com/p/tbm-406-seeing-everything-understanding" class="govuk-link">Seeing Everything, Understanding Nothing (The Context Trap)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://civicworks.substack.com/p/practice-notes-on-including-citizens" class="govuk-link">Practice notes on including citizens in the design process</a></li>
</ul>

      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Narrative - 2 to 6 February</title>
    <link href="/weeknotes/07-02-2026/"/>
    <updated>2026-02-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>/weeknotes/07-02-2026/</id><content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      <![CDATA[
<p class="govuk-body">One of those weeks where so much happens you almost can’t remember any of it. But then you sit down to write about it.</p>
<p class="govuk-body"><strong>Monday</strong>: Started the day learning that a key technical decision underpinning the work we had planned for this quarter was being re-considered, and providing my thoughts to leaders. I can see valid arguments both ways, one side aiming to maintain a more coherent experience for users, the other looking to show something real has changed for the profession.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">As ever I’m thinking of the third way, <a href="https://abicox.medium.com/no-more-big-bang-launches-81f0ce5fdc91" class="govuk-link">avoiding the big bang launch</a>, and supporting users to gradually change their behaviour, moving content and functionality from one platform to another part by part, ideally testing as we go… Floated this around the unit, but ultimately it’s not going to be my call (or at least I don’t have the time to get more involved) and I have to be ok with that. Just need to help the team clearly communicate what can be delivered depending on the final choice, and the point that it’s made.</p>
<p class="govuk-body"><strong>Tuesday</strong>: down to London and back in one day for a long workshop with colleagues across our unit on the future of the same work held up by the above decision. It was great to build some relationships in person and show the value of our team to every one else’s stuff. Most of this stuff is effectively services provided to departments to build their digital ‘capability’ (people). We should be able to sit down properly soon with each team to work out how to better support these services and who needs our help most. Also great to meet the ace new content designer in our team in person!</p>
<p class="govuk-body">A nice surprise was the journey. Getting a train from Sheffield at 8:30, then back from St Pancras at 15:30, meant I can help with the morning routine and get home at a decent time for tea and bedtime (and then pub quiz). Would happily do this again if meeting times allow, so kudos to my manager for the considerate scheduling.</p>
<p class="govuk-body"><strong>Thursday and Friday</strong>: Wins: managed one co-writing session each day with subject matter experts! Less positive: In the first, we learned that one of the main assumptions we were confident in is not right for all the role descriptions, just some of them. But that’s how it goes, by doing the work, we learn what the work is. Second session did make us more confident on that particular role, so overall it’s a draw on the role design front for this week.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">Another thing these sessions reminded me is that no one properly understands the bigger picture of how different standards and frameworks related to our new one are all supposed to relate. So myself and new content designer spent a couple of hours using <a href="https://hpadkisson.medium.com/object-modeling-for-designers-an-introduction-7871bdcf8baf" class="govuk-link">narrative object modelling</a> to map out everything in the domain around the framework. Then, following my own frequent advice to others, shared this work in progress with others in the wider unit and even the cross-government structured information community (gulp). Happily this sparked lots of idea and appreciation in both places, which feels nice. Hopefully it can encourage others to share their work more openly too.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">Amongst near endless onboarding these last couple of weeks, and a fair bit of shadowing, was able to hand over real design work to the new designer, some information architecture scoping, some content 2i. Very pleased to see nothing has phased them so far. They ask good questions, and I think they’re into the heavily strategic profile of the work. Early, but feels like all the effort to recruit well to the role has paid off 🤞.</p>
<p class="govuk-body">Finally I managed to catch up on some plans for the organisation’s design community which are really exciting. I’m keen to make sure all types of designer, in all areas, are being thought about and feel the benefit, but overall it feels like having a Chief Designer in place has helped kicked things up a gear.</p>
<h2 id="to-do" tabindex="-1" class="govuk-heading-l">To do</h2>
<ul class="govuk-list govuk-list--bullet">
<li><a href="https://govservicedesign.net/call-sessions" class="govuk-link"> Propose a session for SDinGov</a> - going along last year was a big highlight, the theme of ‘democracy’ is perfect for our work, and I resolved to get out there more this year, so no excuses whatsoever. Deadline Monday 9 March.</li>
<li>Keep building out this site, maybe write out some case studies.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="reading" tabindex="-1" class="govuk-heading-l">Reading</h2>
<ul class="govuk-list govuk-list--bullet">
<li><a href="https://joelanman.com/posts/govuk-prototype-kit-data/" class="govuk-link">GOV.UK Prototype Kit - Data driven prototyping</a></li>
<li><a href="https://annaecook.com/writing/2026/2/2/accessible-design-is-digital-infrastructure" class="govuk-link">Accessible design is digital infrastructure</a></li>
<li><a href="https://aeon.co/essays/your-brain-does-not-process-information-and-it-is-not-a-computer" class="govuk-link">Your brain does not process information and is not a computer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://contentdesign.london/blog/ai-skills-hub-a-content-critique" class="govuk-link">AI Skills Hub: a content critique</a></li>
</ul>

      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
